I would love to have you share with us
what you think most everybody or even
everybody should know about principles
of strength training principles of
endurance training and principles of
let's call it hypertrophy power in the
other sort of categories of training
what do you think everybody on planet
Earth should know about these categories
of personal and athletic development
well that's a great first question holy
cow there's about nine different
adaptations you can get from exercise um
fat loss is not one of those it is a
byproduct but that's not really what I'm
getting at we can kind of categorize
everything like that and what we're
going to we can talk about are what are
the concepts that you need to hit within
each one and then you can have infinite
discussion of the different
methodologies right and so that that
first thing to hit is the concepts are
actually fairly few but the methods are
many right people have said that in
iterations throughout time so if you
walk from the very beginning the first
one to think about is what we'll just
call skill so this is improving anything
from say a golf swing to a squatting
technique to running this is just simply
moving mechanically how you want your
body to move I'm just going to globally
call that skill from there we're going
to get into speed so this is moving as
fast as possible the next one is power
and power is a function of speed but
it's also a function of the next one
which is strength so if you actually
multiply strength by speed you get power
and the reason I'm making this
distinction by the way is some of these
are very close and I'm going in a
specific order on purpose here for
example power is like I just said it's a
function of speed and strength so if you
improve speed you've also likely
improved power but not necessarily right
because it could have come from the
force Direction either so there's
carryovers so like a lot of things you
would do for the development of strength
and power they are somewhat similar but
there's differences right so things that
you would do correctly for power would
really not develop much strength and
vice versa so we can get into all these
details later once you get past strength
then the next one kind of down the list
is hypertrophy this is muscle size right
growing muscle mass is one way to think
about it after hypertrophy you get into
these categories of the next one is um
these are all globally endurance based
issues and the very first one is called
muscular endurance so this is your
ability to do how many push-ups can you
do in one minute you know things like
that past muscular endurance you're now
into more of an energetic or even
cardiovascular fatigue so you've left
the local muscle and you're now into the
entire physiological system and its
ability to produce and sustain work and
we can get to a bunch of
differentiations within endurance but
I'll just to keep it really simple right
now the very first one think about this
as I call this Anor robic power right so
this is your ability to produce a lot of
work for say 30 seconds to maybe 1
minute kind of two minutes like that the
next one down then is more closely
aligned to what we call your V2 Max so
this is your ability to kind of do the
same thing but more of a Time domain of
say three 3 to 12 minutes so this is
going to be a maximum heart rate but
it's going to be well past just max
heart rate then after that we have what
I call long duration endurance so this
is your ability to sustain work the time
domain doesn't matter in terms of how
fast going you're going it's how long
can you sustain work this is 30 plus
minutes of no break like that so as just
an high level overview those are the
different things you can Target um and
again some of those crossover and some
are actually a little bit contrarian to
the other ones so pushing towards one is
maybe going to sacrifice something else
so as a as an overall start that's
really what we're looking at within all
those though they do have similar
Concepts in terms of there is a handful
of things you have got to do to make all
of those things work and we can talk
about as many of those as you want but
one of them is functionally called
Progressive overload so whichever one
you're trying to improve at if you want
to continue to improve you have to have
some method of overload and as you well
know you've talked about a lot
adaptation physiologically happens as a
byproduct of stress so you have to push
a system so if you continue to do say
the exact same workout over time you
better not expect much improvement you
can keep maintenance but you're not
going to be adding additional stress so
in general you have to have some sort of
progressive overload but this could come
from adding more weights this could come
from adding more repetitions it could
come from doing it more often in the
week it could come from adding
complexity to the movement so going from
say a partial range of motion to a full
range of motion or adding other
variables so there's a lot of different
ways to progress but you have to have
some sort of movement forward so if you
have this kind of routine where you've
built Monday Wednesday and Saturday or
something and you just do that
infinitely um you're not going to get
very far so that's I guess the most high
level overview of all the things people
can go after and then we can go from
whatever Direction you want from there
so if we could start with strength and
hypertrophy I know many people want to
be stronger they want to grow larger
muscles or at least maintain what they
have so what are the progressive
overload principles that are most
effective over time for strength and
hypertrophy yeah okay so I'll actually
go a little step back with every one of
those categories I talked about you have
what we call your modifiable variables
so this is a very short list of all the
things you can modify the different
variables within your workout that can
be modified that will change the outcome
fancy way of saying if you do this
differently then you're going to get a
different result um so modifiable
variables um the very first one of those
is called choice so this is the exercise
choice that you select now one of um I'm
going to go double back here so I'm kind
of doing a little bit of inception so
follow me here as I'm going up a layer
to come down a couple layers I have
these fundamental laws of strength and
conditioning that that I'll they kind of
like a little bit of a joke but
Progressive overlo is one of those laws
another one of those laws is your
exercises themselves do not determine
adaptations so here's what I mean if
you're like I want to get stronger you
can't select an exercise that doesn't
determine you getting strong if you
don't do the exercise correctly and I'm
not even referring to the technique that
of course matters but if you don't
execute it in the right fashion then
you're not going to get that adaptation
so if you choose I want to get stronger
I'm going to do a bench press well if
you do the wrong set range the wrong
repetition range the wrong speed you
won't get strength you maybe get
muscular endurance and very little
strength adaptation so the exercise
selection itself is important but it
does not determine the outcome
adaptation so the very first thing that
you need to think about if you're like I
want to get stronger or add muscle is
not the exercise choice right it is the
application of the exercise what are the
sets what are the Reps what are the rest
ranges that you're using that's going to
be your primary determinant now some
exercises are certainly better for some
adaptations for example um a deadlift is
probably not a great exercise to do for
long duration endurance like you could
theoretically do 30 straight minutes of
deadlifting but it's probably not our
best choice right it's probably a pretty
good choice for strength development
right because you're going to do a low
repetition High set range um you could
theoretically do bicep curls for power
but probably not your best choice right
single joint isolation movement is is
not the best for developing power you've
ever ever done a bicep curl as fast as
you possibly can like that's not going
to go well so in theory any exercise can
produce any adaptation given the
execution is performed properly so now
that we've understood that a little bit
the exercise itself does not determine
the adapt
coming within each one of these
categories exercise choice is an
important variable because it does lend
you to things like what movement pattern
you're in so in other words if if you
want to get stronger and you're thinking
okay what exercise do I do you need to
think think a little bit about what
muscle groups do I want to use and
that's going to be leading you towards
the exercise choice for example I want
to use my quads more okay fine maybe
you're going to choose more of a front
squat type of variation a goblet squat
so the bar the load is in front of you
if you want to emphasize maybe more of
your hamstrings and glutes you're going
to maybe put a barbell on your back or
do a different one so the exercise
choice is important to the prescription
because it's going to determine a lot of
your success okay another kind of
simpler way to think about this if
you're a beginner or moderate to
intermediate or maybe you don't have a
coach you probably want to hedge towards
an exercise selection that is a little
bit easier technically so you maybe
don't want to do a barbell back squat
it's actually a pretty complicated
movement maybe you want to do a little
bit more of um again a goblet squat or
even use some machines or a split squat
something that's a little bit simpler
because you don't have a coach you're
not a professional athlete the
likelihood of success is higher and the
risk is now gone lower so the very first
variable within all of these is the
exercise Choice the second one is the
intensity and that refers to in this
context not perceived effort like wow
that was a really intense workout it is
quite literally either a percentage of
your one rep at Max or a percentage of
your maximum heart rate or V2 Max so for
the strength based things you want to
think about what's percentage of the
maximum weight I could lift one time and
that's that's what we're going to call
one rep max or it's a percentage of my
heart rate right so if I tell you to get
on a bike and I want you to do intervals
and I want you hit 75% I'm typically
referring to 75% of your max heart rate
or V2 Max or you know something like
that if I tell you to do squats at 75%
that means 75% of the maximum amount of
weight you could lift one time or close
the third one is what we call volume and
so this is just how many rep and how
many sets are you doing right so if
you're going to do three sets of 10 that
volume would be 30 right five sets of
five that volume is 25 it's just a
simple equation how much work are you
totally doing uh the next one past that
is called rest intervals so this is the
amount of time you're taking in between
typically a set so all of those things
um can be changed as a method of
progression and so maybe you want to go
progressing from a single joint exercise
like a a leg extension on a machine and
you want to progress by moving to a
whole body movement like a squat that
and of itself you don't have to change
the load or the Reps or the rest that is
a representation of progressive overload
and it's probably a pretty good place to
start because number one especially for
beginners you want to make sure that the
movement pattern is correct don't worry
about intensity don't worry about rep
ranges or any of these things you need
to learn to move correctly and you need
to give your body some time to develop
some tissue tolerance so that you're not
getting overtly sore um in general
soreness is a terrible proxy for
exercise quality it's a really bad way
to estimate whether it was a good or a
bad workout especially for people in
that beginner to Middle to moderate in
fact even that for our professional
athletes um we do not use sorness as a
metric of a good workout it's it's a
really bad idea for a bunch of reasons
on the same token because stress is
required for adaptation you don't want
to leave at the gym and feel like I
don't really do much like there has to
be there so if you think about soreness
on a scale of 1 to 10 you probably want
to spend most of your time in like the
three you mean post exercise
yeah in between workouts totally and I I
know we'll talk about recovery
extensively later but uh if one body
part or set of body parts is sore is
that an indication that one should stay
out of training I would imagine the
answer is no in most cases um and
secondarily to that if a particular
muscle is sore does that mean that
muscle is not ready to be trained again
yeah the answer to both those is the
same um which is no right um You can
train a sore muscle you you need to I
guess have a little bit of feel on that
right so if if you're sore of like okay
like and you're moving around a little
bit you're like man this is a little bit
sore you can train if you're like I
can't sit on the couch without crying
because my glutes are so sore like we we
probably don't need to train again right
we do whimpering count as
crying yeah uh in that particular case
I'd say you've actually gone to the
place of
detriment because now you're going to
have to skip a training session and now
you're behind so your actual total
volume say across the month is actually
going to be lower because you went way
too hard in those workouts had to take
too many days off in between you're
going to see that you're going to cover
less distance over the course of a month
or six month or even a year so you want
to walk a pretty fine line and for most
people I would say hedge a little bit on
the side of less sore than more sore
because frequency is very very important
for almost all these adaptations at
training frequency which is the last
modifiable variable right frequency
which is how many times per week are you
are you doing that thing so those are um
kind of our our Global things that we
can play with so when I'm trying to
manipulate and get strength versus
hypertrophy or you know what I want like
a little bit of both all those variables
are the things that are going through my
mind which one do I need to move in
which direction so that I can get this
outcome and not this outcome over here
for example some folks might want to get
stronger but not put muscle mass on some
folks are just kind of want both
and that's a lot of the general public I
want to get a little stronger and a
little bit more muscle great but there
are instances where people for
performance reasons or for purely
personal preference like I don't want to
get any more muscle great but I want to
get stronger awesome if you manipulate
those variables correctly you can get
exactly that very little development of
muscle size and a lot of development in
strength and this is why we continue to
break World Records in sports like
powerlifting and weightlifting that have
weight classes so there's a top number
that we can hit in terms of body size
but yet we continue to get stronger and
faster so this is very possible if you
understand how to manipulate all those
variables click the link in our bio to
get instant and free access to our
hypertrophy highlights fireside chat
which is Dan and I discussing really
personal aspects of how we go about
programming for muscle hypertrophy in
that chat you're going to hear Dan and I
talk about our own experiences working
with clients who are trying to add
muscle mass and especially you're going
to hear us tell some stories that you've
never heard us talk about in any podcast
ever before this is not something you're
going to want to miss